<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Annotations by Pablo Caro - health</title><link href="https://pablocaro.es/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pablocaro.es/feeds/tags/health.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pablocaro.es/en/</id><updated>2025-12-25T14:45:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Annotations</subtitle><entry><title>OpenEvidence: The Leading Medical Information Platform for Professionals</title><link href="https://pablocaro.es/en/open-evidence-plataforma-medica" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-12-25T14:45:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T14:45:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Caro</name></author><id>tag:pablocaro.es,2025-12-25:/en/open-evidence-plataforma-medica</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Exploring OpenEvidence, a leading platform that consolidates medical information, clinical findings, and practice guidelines for healthcare professionals in the US.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the healthcare field, quick and reliable access to the latest and relevant medical information is crucial for clinical decision-making. &lt;strong&gt;OpenEvidence&lt;/strong&gt; positions itself as a leading platform designed to consolidate and present this information in an accessible way to healthcare professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-does-openevidence-offer"&gt;What Does OpenEvidence Offer?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#what-does-openevidence-offer" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenEvidence acts as a nerve center for medical information, signing content agreements with some of the most prestigious publications and organizations in the sector. Its collaborators include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The New England Journal of Medicine (NEJM)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JAMA Network&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN)&lt;/strong&gt;, including its clinical guidelines and pathways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mayo Clinic Platform&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ensures that professionals have at their fingertips an authoritative and updated source of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-features-for-professionals"&gt;Key Features for Professionals&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#key-features-for-professionals" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The platform is designed to meet the specific needs of healthcare professionals, offering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;: Direct access to clinical findings and original research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patient Documents&lt;/strong&gt;: Tools to create informative brochures for patients, facilitating communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capabilities Exploration&lt;/strong&gt;: An intuitive system to navigate through a vast library of resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical Guidelines and Pathways&lt;/strong&gt;: Access to the latest recommendations for the treatment and management of various conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="who-is-it-for"&gt;Who is it For?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#who-is-it-for" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenEvidence is aimed primarily at &lt;strong&gt;verified healthcare professionals in the US&lt;/strong&gt; and is offered free of charge for this group. It is available through iOS and Android apps, allowing convenient and mobile access to information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#conclusion" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenEvidence represents a significant advance in the democratization of access to high-quality medical information. By consolidating resources from various authoritative sources and offering them on an easy-to-use platform, it allows healthcare professionals to make more informed decisions and, ultimately, improve patient care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Official website&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href="https://www.openevidence.com/"&gt;OpenEvidence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Miscellaneous"></category><category term="open-evidence"></category><category term="medicine"></category><category term="health"></category><category term="medical-information"></category><category term="health-professionals"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="clinical"></category></entry></feed>