<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Annotations by Pablo Caro - yakuake</title><link href="https://pablocaro.es/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://pablocaro.es/feeds/tags/yakuake.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://pablocaro.es/en/</id><updated>2025-12-25T12:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>Annotations</subtitle><entry><title>From Yakuake to Kitty: My Transition to a Modern Terminal</title><link href="https://pablocaro.es/en/de-yakuake-a-kitty" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-12-25T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-25T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Pablo Caro</name></author><id>tag:pablocaro.es,2025-12-25:/en/de-yakuake-a-kitty</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Exploring the reasons and benefits of switching from Yakuake to Kitty for a more powerful and customizable terminal experience.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For years, &lt;strong&gt;Yakuake&lt;/strong&gt; has been my go-to terminal in KDE desktop environments. Its quick access convenience, dropping down and hiding with a simple keystroke, is undeniable. However, in my constant search for optimization and performance, I decided to explore alternatives, and &lt;strong&gt;Kitty&lt;/strong&gt; emerged as a standout option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-the-switch"&gt;Why the Switch?&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#why-the-switch" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Yakuake is excellent in its niche, Kitty offers a series of advantages that align better with the demands of a modern and demanding workflow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPU Accelerated Performance&lt;/strong&gt;: Kitty is designed to leverage the graphics card, resulting in extremely fast and fluid text rendering, especially noticeable in terminals with a lot of scrolling or intense output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Multiplexing&lt;/strong&gt;: Unlike Yakuake, which relies on traditional tab/window sessions, Kitty incorporates its own multiplexing system (similar to &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt;) that allows splitting windows, creating tabs, and organizing panes natively and efficiently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extensive Configurability&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;kitty.conf&lt;/code&gt; allows deep customization, from keyboard shortcuts to appearance, themes, and behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Support&lt;/strong&gt;: Excellent support for Wayland (the future of Linux on the desktop), font ligatures (like Fira Code), and an ecosystem of "kittens" (scripts and extended functionalities).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-platform&lt;/strong&gt;: Although my main use is on Linux, the ability to have a consistent terminal experience across different operating systems is a plus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="adapting-to-kitty"&gt;Adapting to Kitty&lt;a class="headerlink" href="#adapting-to-kitty" title="Permanent link"&gt;&amp;para;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transition required adjusting some habits, mainly the way sessions and quick access are managed. However, the advantages far outweigh the initial learning curve. The speed, fluidity, and power of Kitty's built-in features make it an indispensable tool for my daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configuring Kitty is a simple process through its &lt;code&gt;kitty.conf&lt;/code&gt; file, where all aspects of the terminal are defined. We will explore more about its configuration and keyboard shortcuts in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking to take your terminal experience to the next level, migrating to Kitty is a step I highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Systems"></category><category term="kitty"></category><category term="yakuake"></category><category term="terminal"></category><category term="linux"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="tools"></category></entry></feed>